[Music]
[Applause]
Hamlin towns in Brunswick by famous
hannover City the river of azar deep and
wide washes its wall on the southern
side a pleasant a spot you never spied
but when begins my ditty almost 500
years ago to see the town's folks suffer
so from vermin was a pity
[Music]
I bought the dog and killed the cats and
pit the babies in the cradles and ed the
cheese's out of the vats and licked the
soup from the cooks own ladles split
open the kegs of salted sprouts made
nests inside minced sunday hats and even
spoiled the women's chats by drowning
their speaking with shrieking and
speaking in 50 different sharps and
flats
[Music]
[Applause]
at last the people in a body to the town
hall came flocking tis clear cried they
are mares are Noddy and as for our
corporation sucking to think we buy
gowns lined with ermine for dotes that
can't or won't determine what's best to
rid us of our farming you hope because
you're older no beasts defined in the
furry Civic Roby's browsers give your
brains are wrecking to find the remedy
were lacking or surahs fate will send
you packing
[Applause]
at this the mayor and corporation quaked
with a mighty consternation
[Applause]
an hour they sat in Council at length
the mayor broke silence for a Guilder
I'd my arm in gum sell my wish I were a
mile hence it's easy to bid one rack
one's brain and so my poor head aches
again I've scratched it so and all in
vain Oh for a trap a trap just as he
said this what should happen the chamber
door but a gentle tap
scored the mare what's that with the
cooperation as he sat looking little the
wondrous fat nor brighter was his eye
nor moister than a too long opened a
stir say when at noon his paunch grew
mutinous for a plate of turtle green and
glutinous only a scraping of shoes on
the mat anything like the sound of a rat
makes my heart go pit-a-pat
come in mmm the mayor cried looking
bigger and indeed come the strangest
figure his queer long coat from heel to
head was half of yellow and half of red
and he himself was tall and thin with
sharp blue eyes each like a pinned with
light loose hair its swarthy skin had no
tuft on cheek no beard on chin but lips
we're smiles went out and in there was
no guessing his kith and kin and nobody
could enough admire the tall man and his
quaint attire quoth one it has my
great-grandson starting up at the Trump
of Doom stone and walked this way from
his painted tools too he advanced to the
council table and please your honor said
he I'm able by means of a secret charm
to draw all creatures living beneath the
Sun that creep or swim or fly or run
after me so as you never saw and I
chiefly use my charm on creatures that
do people harm the mole and toad and
Newt and Pfeiffer and people call me the
Pied Piper
[Music]
and here they noticed round his neck a
scarf of red and yellow stripe to match
with his coat of the self-same check and
at the scarfs end on the pipe and his
fingers they noticed wherever straying
as if impatient to be playing upon this
pipe as low it dangled over his vest
jostle old Frankel's yet city poor Piper
as I am in Tartary I freed the charm
last June from his huge swarms of gnats
I eased in Asia the nizam of a monstrous
blue little vampire bat hmm and as for
what your brain bewildered if I can rid
your town of rats will you give me a
thousand guilders sixty thousand was the
exclamation of the astonished man
incorporate
[Applause]
into the street the piper stepped
smiling first a little smile as if he
knew what magic slept in his quiet pipe
of the while then like a musical adept
the blowpipe his lips hearing cooled and
green and blue his sharp eyes twinkled
like a candle flame where softy
sprinkled and ere three shrill notes the
pipe uh turned
[Music]
[Applause]
you heard as if an army muttered
[Music]
muttering grumbling grumbling grew to a
mighty rumbling and out of the houses
the rats came tumbling great rats small
lean rats brawny rat's run rats rats
rats brave old young viscous cooking
tails and flicking whiskers families by
tens and dozens brothers sisters
husbands wives followed the paper for
their lives
[Music]
subscribe to Street he piped advancing
and step for step they follow dancing
[Music]
until they came to the river visa we're
in all lungs and parrots
[Music]
save one who stutters Julius Caesar swam
across and lived to carry as he the
manuscript he cherished to Rockland home
his commentary which was at the first
trill notes of the pipe I heard a sound
as of scraping tripe and putting apples
wondrous rekt into a cider press his
gripe and a moving away of pickled
companies and our leaving a jar of
conserved companies and a drawing the
of train oil flasks and a breaking
the hoops of butter casks and it seemed
as if a voice sweeter father and the
world is grown to one vast and just as a
spunky sugar pumpkin already stays like
a great glorious gas an inch before me
just as me thought it said Khan born
I found the phaser rolling normy
[Music]
you should have heard the Hamline people
ringing the bells to layer up the
steeple
[Applause]
[Music]
Oh cried the mayor and get long palms
[Applause]
and leave in our town not even a trace
of the rats could suddenly up the face
of the pipe upper did marketplace with a
first if you please my thousand guilders
a thousand guilders the mayor looked
blue so did the corporation to four
council dinners made rare havoc with
claret Moselle van de graaff hoc and
half the money would replenish their
cellars biggest but with Rhenish to pay
this sum to a wandering fella with a
gypsy coat of red and yellow beside
quoth the mare with a knowing wink our
business was done at the rivers brink we
saw with our eyes the vermin sink and
what dead can't come to life I think
it's our friend we're not the folks to
shrink from the duty of giving you
something for drink but no matter of
money to put in your poke but as for the
guilders what we spoke of them as you
very well know was it joke beside our
losses have made us thrifty the thousand
guilders come take 50
the Piper's face fell and he cried no
trifling I can't wait
beside I've promised a visit by
dinnertime Baghdad and accept the prime
of the head cooks pottage all he's rich
in for having left in the Caliph's
kitchen of a nest of scorpions no
survivor with him I proved no bargain
driver with you don't think I'll bait us
divert and folks who put me in a passion
may find me pipe after another fashion
Oh cried the man you think I broke being
worse treated than a cook insulted by a
lazy rye bald with idle pipe and vesture
piebald
you threaten us fellow do your worst
blow you pink there till you burst once
more he stepped into the street and to
his lips again laid his long pipe of
smooth straight came and there he blew
three notes
[Music]
such sweet soft notes as yet musicians
cunning never gave the enraptured air
[Music]
there was a wrestling that seemed like a
bustling no Mary crowds just linger
pitchy bustling small feet were
pattering wooden shoes clattering little
hands clapping and little tongues
chattering and like fowls in a farmyard
when Bali's scattering out came the
children running
[Music]
all the little boys and girls with rosy
cheeks and flaxen curls and sparkling
eyes of teeth like pearls tripping and
skipping around merrily after the
wonderful music with shouting and
laughter
[Music]
the mouth was done and the consul's
doomed as if they were changed into
blocks of wood unable to move a step
I'll cry to the children merrily
skipping by could only follow with the
eye that joyous crowd at the Piper's
back but Harlan Mayor was on the rack
and the Richard councils bosoms beat as
the piper turned from the high street to
where the Vaes are rolled its waters
right in the way of their sons and
daughters
[Music]
however he turned from south to West and
to Kapil bag Hillard his Stella so
dressed and after him the children
oppressed great was the joy in every
breast he never can crossed that mighty
top he's forced to let the piping drop
and we shall see our children stopped
[Music]
when lo as they reached the mountainside
how wondrous portal opened wide as if a
cavern was suddenly hollowed and the
piper advanced and the children followed
[Music]
[Applause]
and when all with him to the very last
the door in the mountainside
[Music]
did I say oh no one was lame and could
not dance the whole of the way and in
after years if you would blame his
sadness he was used to say it's dull in
our town since my playmates left they
can't forget that I'm the raft of all
the pleasant sights they see push the
piper also promised me free lettuce he
said to a joyous land joining the town
and just at hand were waters gushed and
fruit trees drew and flowers put forth a
fairy yield and everything was strange
and new the sparrows were brighter than
peacocks here and there dogs are ran our
fallow deer then honeybees had lost
their stings and horses were born with
eagle's wings and just as I became
assured my lame foot would be speedily
cured the music stopped when I stood
still and find myself outside Dale left
alone against my will to go now limping
as before and never hear of that country
more alas alas for Hammond Lee
that came in too many a burghers paint a
text which says that Heaven's Gate Oaks
to the rich that his easy rates as the
needles I takes a camel the mayor sent
east west north and south to offer the
piper by word-of-mouth wherever it was
men's lot to find him silver and go to
his heart's content if he'd only
returned the way he went and bring the
children behind him but when they sought
was a lost endeavor and Piper and
dancers were gone forever
they made a decree that lawyers never
should think their records dated duly if
after the day of the month and year
these words did not as well appear and
so long after what happened here on the
22nd of July thirteen hundred and
seventy-six and the better in memory to
fix the place of the children's last
retreat they called it the Pied Pipers
Street but anyone playing on pipe or
Tabor was sure over the future to lose
his labor nor suffered a hostelry or
tavern to shock with mirth a street so
solemn but opposite the place of the
cavern they wrote the story on a column
and on the great church window painted
the same to make the world acquainted
how their children was stolen away
then it stands to this very day
and I must not omit to say that in
Transylvania there's a tribe of alien
people who ascribed the outlandish ways
and dress in which the neighbors lay
such stress to their fathers and mothers
having risen out of some subterraneous
prison into which they were trap and
long time ago in a mighty band out of
Hamelin town in Brunswick land but how
or why they don't understand
so Willie and me and you be wipers of
scores out with all men especially Piper
and whether they pay us free from rats
off from mice if we promised the moment
let us keep the promise
[Music]
[Applause]